<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>git-subrepo</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">Git</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Git Manual</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>git-subrepo</refname>
  <refpurpose>Add and update subrepos</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id="_synopsis">
<literallayout><emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> add [--edit] [--verbose] &lt;remote-repository&gt; &lt;prefix&gt; &lt;commit&gt;
<emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> update [--edit] [--verbose] &lt;remote-repository&gt; &lt;prefix&gt; &lt;commit&gt;</literallayout>
<simpara></simpara>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Adds and updates subrepos.</simpara>
<simpara>A subrepo allows you to keep another Git repository in a subdirectory
of your current repository (the current repository is termed the
"superrepo"). The other repository&#8217;s source code is thereby embedded
directly into this repository. This embedding makes subrepos preferable
to submodules (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-submodule</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>) in many scenarios, as
references to another repository cannot become invalid and all
dependencies required in the superrepo are contained in it. In that
sense, subrepos behave similar to subtrees (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-subtree</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>)
when using the --squash option to squash commits. The resulting commit,
however, is not a merge in any way. Rather, the source code is imported
as a "normal" commit, allowing for rebasing to take place, for instance.</simpara>
<simpara>Being part of the superrepo, clone and pull operations will involve any
subrepos equally well, without any additional command invocations being
required.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_commands">
<title>COMMANDS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
add
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Add the given remote repository as a subrepo at the given prefix/path
  in the state as specified by the given commit. A new commit will be
  created in the superrepo that imports the source code.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
update
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Update an existing subrepo so that the state of the source code in the
  subdirectory specified by the given prefix matches that of the remote
  repository at the given commit. A new commit will be created in the
  superrepo that contains the differences between the state before
  and after the update.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;remote-repository&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Name of a remote repository to import in the form of a subrepo. The
  remote repository should be up-to-date such that the given commit is
  known locally. Please refer to <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-remote</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> for more details
  on remote repositories.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;prefix&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Relative path specifying where to add a new subrepo or where an
  already imported one to update resides.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;commit&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Commit representing the state at which to import the given remote
  repository as a subrepo or to which to update the given subrepo to.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-e
</term>
<term>
--edit
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  By default git-subrepo creates a commit message containing only the
  essential information for a particular commit. When this option is set
  the committer gets the chance to further edit the message.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-v
</term>
<term>
--verbose
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  In normal mode of operation git-subrepo only prints messages in case
  of errors. For debugging purposes it might be beneficial to understand
  which commands are being executed and possibly replay them. By
  specifying this option all command invocations are reported to the
  user.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>To be used in conjunction with the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> suite</simpara>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
