<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>git-subrepo</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">Git</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Git Manual</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>git-subrepo</refname>
  <refpurpose>Subrepo management for git</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id="_synopsis">
<literallayout><emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> [--debug-commands] [--debug-exceptions]
<emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> import [--edit] [--force] &lt;remote-repository&gt; &lt;prefix&gt; &lt;commit&gt;
<emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> delete [--edit] &lt;subrepo&gt; &lt;prefix&gt;
<emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> reimport [--branch=&lt;branch&gt;] [--verbose] &lt;subrepo&gt; &lt;prefix&gt;
<emphasis>git subrepo</emphasis> tree</literallayout>
<simpara></simpara>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Imports a subrepo at a given prefix representing a given commit.</simpara>
<simpara>A subrepo allows you to keep another Git repository in a subdirectory
of your current repository (the current repository is termed the
"superrepo"). The other repository&#8217;s source code is thereby embedded
directly into this repository. This embedding makes subrepos preferable
to submodules (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-submodule</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>) in many scenarios, as
references to another repository cannot become invalid and all
dependencies required in the superrepo are contained in it. In that
sense, subrepos behave similar to subtrees (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-subtree</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>)
when using the --squash option to squash commits. The resulting commit,
however, is not a merge in any way. Rather, the source code is imported
as a "normal" commit, allowing for rebasing to take place, for instance.</simpara>
<simpara>Being part of the superrepo, clone and pull operations will involve any
subrepos equally well, without any additional command invocations being
required.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_commands">
<title>COMMANDS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
import
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Import the given remote repository as a subrepo at the given
  prefix/path in the state as specified by the given commit. A new
  commit will be created in the superrepo that imports the source code.
  This command handles initial additions as well as incremental updates.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
delete
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Delete a subrepo previously imported at the given prefix. A new commit
  will be created to remove the code. The command takes care of
  resolving dependencies properly. That is, if two subrepos, <emphasis>a</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>b</emphasis>, pull in a third one, <emphasis>c</emphasis>, deletion of either <emphasis>a</emphasis> or <emphasis>b</emphasis> will not
  delete <emphasis>c</emphasis>. Only once both subrepos <emphasis>a</emphasis> and <emphasis>b</emphasis> get removed, the last
  deletion will delete <emphasis>c</emphasis> as well.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
reimport
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Check whether current <emphasis>HEAD</emphasis> commit is a subrepo import and, if so,
  check whether a newer version of the imported commit can be found. If
  that is the case then reimport the remote repository at this new
  state. Matching of commits is performed based on the subject line of
  the commit description.
  This command is useful if imported remote repositories are rebased
  remotely. If the new state is to be imported not as a separate new
  commit but by amending the original import commit, this command takes
  care of importing the updated source code and adjusting the import
  commit message.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
tree
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Print out the subrepo dependency tree.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;remote-repository&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Name of a remote repository to import in the form of a subrepo. The
  remote repository should be up-to-date such that the given commit is
  known locally. Please refer to <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-remote</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> for more details
  on remote repositories.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;subrepo&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Name of a subrepo to delete.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;prefix&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Relative path specifying where to import a subrepo or from where to
  delete it. On import, if code exists at the given prefix the
  differences to reach the desired state of the specified remote
  repository will be applied on top.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;commit&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Commit representing the state at which to import the given remote
  repository as a subrepo or to which to update the given subrepo to.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-b
</term>
<term>
--branch
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  When performing a reimport, matching commits (those with the same
  subject line as the imported commit) are searched across branches.
  That is, if there are multiple branches containing two equally worded
  commits with different SHA-1 hashes, both will be found leading to the
  reimport to be ambiguous and, hence, aborted. To pick a commit from
  one of the branches this option followed by the branch name can be
  used.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--debug-commands
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  In normal mode of operation git-subrepo only prints messages in case
  of errors. For debugging purposes it might be beneficial to understand
  which commands are being executed and possibly replay them. By
  specifying this option all command invocations are reported to the
  user.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--debug-exceptions
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  In the usual case git-subrepo prints an error in case one of the
  executed git commands failed. When the --debug-exceptions flag is
  specified a backtrace will be printed in addition, potentially helping
  in debugging issues.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-e
</term>
<term>
--edit
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  By default git-subrepo creates a commit message containing only the
  essential information for a particular commit. When this option is set
  the committer gets the chance to further edit the message.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-f
</term>
<term>
--force
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  As a sanity check, git-subrepo verifies that a commit at which to
  import a given remote repository in the form of a subrepo does indeed
  belong to the remote repository specified. By using this option this
  check can be omitted and an import be forced.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-v
</term>
<term>
--verbose
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
  Be more verbose during a reimport by displaying the previous import
  commit as well as the new one.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_root_imports">
<title>ROOT IMPORTS</title>
<simpara>One advantage of subrepos over git&#8217;s native submodules is the fact that
the source code of the destination is embedded in the repository. The
ability to have ordinary commits as opposed to merges as they are
created when subtrees are in use is beneficial for rebasing over
imports.</simpara>
<simpara>However, there is another feature that is unique to subrepos: the
ability to import remote repositories directly into the root directory
of the owning repository. Consider the following example:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">lib1
└── src
    └── lib1.py</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">lib2
└── src
    ├── lib1
    │   └── src
    │       └── lib1.py
    └── lib2.py</literallayout>
<simpara>In this example we have two libraries, <emphasis>lib1</emphasis> and <emphasis>lib2</emphasis>. The latter
depends on the former and, hence, imports it in the form of a subrepo.
Now imagine an application, <emphasis>app</emphasis>, using <emphasis>lib2</emphasis>. Once <emphasis>app</emphasis> imports
<emphasis>lib2</emphasis> it will implicitly import <emphasis>lib1</emphasis> as well (which is intended
because it is an implicit dependency).</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">app
└── src
    ├── app.py
    └── lib2
        └── src
            ├── lib1
            │   └── src
            │       └── lib1.py
            └── lib2.py</literallayout>
<simpara>With each import the level of nesting increases. Not only that, there is
also a non-uniformity in the directory layout: the source code in the
owning repository is scattered counter-intuitively over different
directory levels, making it unnecessarily complex to find files. These
problems are inherent the moment a repository starts having
subdirectories.
Such problems vanish when we restructure the repositories slightly and
then import each directly into the owning repository&#8217;s root directory,
like so:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">lib1
└── lib1
    └── src
        └── lib1.py</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">lib2
├── lib1
│   └── src
│       └── lib1.py
└── lib2
    └── src
        └── lib2.py</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">app
├── app
│   └── src
│       └── app.py
├── lib1
│   └── src
│       └── lib1.py
└── lib2
    └── src
        └── lib2.py</literallayout>
<simpara>Now an interesting question arises: since the root name space of the
owning repository is shared, how are conflicts handled? The answer is
simple: the last import will take precedence and applied are the changes
from the current state of the owning repository to one where the subrepo
to import is at the desired state.</simpara>
<simpara>This approach also solves another otherwise inherent problem, namely
that if each subrepo pulls in its dependencies and two subrepos have the
same dependency, the source code of this last dependency will reside in
the repository at two places. From a logical point of view that is not
necessary a problem. However, if one considers how the module systems of
a variety of languages or their compilers/interpreters work it becomes
apparent that one of the two is effectively dead code: the path to each
subrepo has to be registered somewhere and this path will be searched
for a match during compile or run time. Yet, only the first match that
is found is used. This constraint in turn implies that both versions of
the subrepo need to be "compatible" if they are to be used in a common
application and we must be able to agree on using a single version.</simpara>
<simpara>Extending the example from before with a third library, <emphasis>lib3</emphasis> that
depends on <emphasis>lib1</emphasis> as well, and making <emphasis>app</emphasis> require <emphasis>lib3</emphasis> in addition
to <emphasis>lib2</emphasis>, we get away with the following structure:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">app
├── app
│   └── src
│       └── app.py
├── lib1
│   └── src
│       └── lib1.py
├── lib2
│   └── src
│       └── lib2.py
└── lib3
    └── src
        └── lib3.py</literallayout>
<simpara>Here, <emphasis>lib1</emphasis> is used by both <emphasis>lib2</emphasis> and <emphasis>lib3</emphasis> without the need to have
a private copy in each. By design, it must be compatible with both.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_examples">
<title>EXAMPLES</title>
<simpara>Assuming two repositories, <emphasis>lib</emphasis> and <emphasis>app</emphasis>, that initially do not know
each other but are located in the same directory, the following example
illustrates how to import the former as a subrepo of the latter:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ cd app/
$ git remote add -f lib ../lib/</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>At this point <emphasis>lib</emphasis> is known to <emphasis>app</emphasis>.</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ git subrepo import lib . master</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>This command pulls in the contents of <emphasis>lib</emphasis> into the root directory of
<emphasis>app</emphasis>. A new commit will be created in <emphasis>app</emphasis> that contains the changes
that were made.</simpara>
<simpara>It is also possible to import the remote repository into any other
directory, e.g., foo/:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ git subrepo import lib foo/ master</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>Imagine that <emphasis>lib</emphasis> is now being updated.</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ cd ../lib/
$ edit hello.c
$ git commit --message 'update' hello.c</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>If we want to have these changes in <emphasis>app</emphasis> we can update the subrepo:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ cd ../app/
$ git fetch lib
$ git subrepo import lib foo/ master</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>Now the subrepo <emphasis>lib</emphasis> in directory foo/ contains the most recent state
of the original <emphasis>lib</emphasis> while the one imported into the root is still at
the previous state.</simpara>
<simpara>The current state of imports can be visualized using the <emphasis>tree</emphasis> command:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ git subrepo tree
├── foo/:lib at e6a02545285d187ae0f5c3211421f736a5092b65
└── ./:lib at 8b3f9546e3dd4ea68f457cdc60859b2f4a342984</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>The output illustrates that the remote repository <emphasis>lib</emphasis> has been
imported at two prefixes, the root of the repository and the directory
foo/. It also depicts the commit at which the import happened.</simpara>
<simpara>There are cases possible where the history of <emphasis>lib</emphasis> is (partly)
rewritten. For instance, imagine that the commits have not been
published anywhere because development is still going on in private and
a bug was found and fixed. Updating the imports of <emphasis>lib</emphasis> in <emphasis>app</emphasis> can
happen using the reimport command. For example:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ git rebase --interactive HEAD^^^ --exec='git subrepo reimport'</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>During the development of our <emphasis>app</emphasis> we may decide that we no longer need
the version of <emphasis>lib</emphasis> imported below foo/. We could just remove the files
by hand but that is cumbersome and would require manually taking care of
handling dependencies correctly. Instead, we can delete the subrepo like
so:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">$ git subrepo delete lib foo/</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>To be used in conjunction with the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> suite</simpara>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
